Second Dish
Episode 2
Yukihira
Souma
The victor in the first match
of the Autumn Elections is...
Yukihira
Souma
（川島麗(かわしまうらら)）秋の選抜 本戦
第一試合 勝者は…
Yukihira
Souma
（薙切(なきり)アリス）
うっ うう… ああ～！
Yukihira
Souma
（麗）幸平創真選手！
Yukihira
Souma
Candidate Yukihira Souma!
Yukihira
Souma
Glad you liked it!
（幸平創真(ゆきひらそうま)）御粗末！
He won!
（水戸(みと)郁魅(いくみ)）勝ったぁ！
（吉野悠姫(よしのゆうき)）しゅごい～！
Woohoo!
ああああ～ん！
うっ ううう…
C'mon, don't cry like a kid just
because you lost.
（創真）
あ～あ　負けたからって
子供みてえに…
（創真）
あ～あ　負けたからって
子供みてえに…
（アリスの泣き声）
Stand up.
ほら 立て
むうう…
Thank—
（アリス）ありが…
（創真）次代の十傑(じゅっけつ)争い―
Guess I'm now one step ahead of you
in the fight to become
one of the next Elite Ten.
俺の１歩リードってとこだな
What?!
何よ！　勝ったからって
偉そうにしないでちょうだい！
Don't act all high and mighty
just because you won!
言っておきます
私は このままでは終わらない
Let me tell you something.
This isn't the last you'll see of me!
I'm not going to let you have
the top seat at Tohtsuki!
遠月(とおつき)の頂点は
譲らないんだから
ご機嫌よう 幸平君
Have a good day, Yukihira-kun!
んっ…
あ…
I guess your skills are not that impressive.
（薙切(なきり)えりな）
実力の底が知れたわね
（アリス）はっ…
何よ 何よ 何よぉ！
What? What? What?!
I guess you're a genius not only at cooking but also at insults!
えりなは料理だけじゃなくて
悪口のセンスも天才級だわ！
You do realize you're
complimenting my cooking?
（えりな）
それ 料理に関しては
褒めちゃってるわよ
Listen!
いいこと？　私がリベンジするまで
待ってなさいよね
Just wait till I get my revenge!
Stupid Erina!
えりなのバカ！
I envy you.
（えりな）いいわね あなたは
You can just cry like that whenever you want.
そうやって
気ままに泣けるんだもの
ああ～…
Souma-kun.
（田所恵(たどころめぐみ)）創真君！
（創真）あ？
I was watching from the standby room.
控室で見てたよ
Congratulations!
おめでとう！
Thanks, Tadokoro.
（創真）おお 田所　出番だな
It's your turn, huh?
You look pretty calm.
何か落ち着いてるじゃんか
Am I?
そうかな？
I guess so!
そうかも
See, I could only think
of trying my best in the prelims.
（恵）あのね 予選の時は―
ただ精一杯やることしか
頭になかったんだけど―
今は 自分の料理を
楽しめたらって―
But now, I'm hoping
to enjoy my own cooking.
It's the first time I've felt this way!
初めて そんなふうに
思えてるんだ
I see.
そっか
ま 気張らず行ってきな
Well, try not to get too tense.
Good luck!
頑張れ！
Thanks!
うん！
（足音）
（黒木場(くろきば)リョウ）
相変わらず
料理が きれいすぎる
Your cooking's too pretty, as usual.
Are you trying to lecture me?
私に説教をしているの？
わきまえなさい
Know your place.
I believe I do know my place.
（黒木場）
もちろん わきまえた上で
話してますが
Anyway, miss... you should save that line
それに お嬢
そういうセリフは―
for when you beat me in cooking.
料理で俺に勝ち越してから
言ってくださいよ
（麗）
続いて一回戦 第二試合
選手の入場です！
Next is the second match in the first round!
The candidates are coming in!
（観客の歓声）
（麗）ここでダークホースが登場
Here is our dark horse candidate, Candidate Tadokoro Megumi,
who passed the Block B preliminaries at the very last minute!
Ｂブロックで
最後の最後に予選通過を決めた―
Good luck!
田所恵選手です！
Her opponent is Candidate Kurokiba Ryou,
対するは 予選ではＡブロック―
who was tied with Candidate Yukihira Souma for second place in the Block A preliminaries!
幸平選手と同じ ２位タイで通過
黒木場リョウ選手！
The theme...
対決テーマは―
Match 2
Ramen
is ramen!
Match 2
Ramen
ラーメンです！
Match 2
Ramen
ええーい！
Let the cooking begin!
（薙切仙左衛門(なきりせんざえもん)）調理 開始！
♪～
omoiegaiteru imeeji yori haruka mukou gawa e
Far beyond the image I have in my mind
tsukuriagete yuku shinjitsu wa mada tooku
The reality I'm building up is still far away
hatenai tabiji
An endless journey
otagai no puraido wo togisumaseyou ze
Let's hone each other's pride
kotoba nante kazari wa
Words aren't really important
hai dakyou saseba ii
So let's just say "yes" and leave it at that
butsukariai migakarete iku
We fight each other and hone our skills
No reason
Our encounters cause shockwaves
deai wa shockwave shockwave
We're reckless challengers
mada shiranai sekai e
Heading toward a world as yet unexplored
arukihajimeta mubou na chousensha sa
A swordsman should use his blade
kenshi ga yaiba de ashita wo
To open the way to the future
kirihirakeba iin darou
This is my story and no one else's
dareka no mon ja nai jibun dake no story
Cause we are still rough diamonds on the road
～♪
THE INTERPLAY OF LIGHT AND SHADOW
（鳥の鳴き声）
（一色慧(いっしきさとし)）
大まかな説明は以上だ
That concludes the general overview.
PREVIOUS DAY
One last thing: we'll provide the noodles.
そして最後に
もう一点だが―
麺は こちらで
用意させてもらう
（恵）あ…
The match is tomorrow, after all.
本番は明日だからね
We made the noodles
in advance to let them rest.
前もって 麺の熟成を
進めておいたのさ
Noodle Type
Thickness
Straight Noodles
Curly Noodles
Flat/Wide Noodles
Egg Noodles
Noodle Type
Thickness
Straight Noodles
Curly Noodles
Flat/Wide Noodles
Egg Noodles
Noodle Type
Thickness
Straight Noodles
Curly Noodles
Flat/Wide Noodles
Egg Noodles
Noodle Type
Thickness
Straight Noodles
Curly Noodles
Flat/Wide Noodles
Egg Noodles
Noodle Type
Thickness
Straight Noodles
Curly Noodles
Flat/Wide Noodles
Egg Noodles
Noodle Type
Thickness
Straight Noodles
Curly Noodles
Flat/Wide Noodles
Egg Noodles
Noodle Type
Thickness
Straight Noodles
Curly Noodles
Flat/Wide Noodles
Egg Noodles
Noodle Type
Thickness
Straight Noodles
Curly Noodles
Flat/Wide Noodles
Egg Noodles
Noodle Type
Thickness
Straight Noodles
Curly Noodles
Flat/Wide Noodles
Egg Noodles
Noodle Type
Thickness
Straight Noodles
Curly Noodles
Flat/Wide Noodles
Egg Noodles
Noodle Type
Thickness
Straight Noodles
Curly Noodles
Flat/Wide Noodles
Egg Noodles
Noodle Type
Thickness
Straight Noodles
Curly Noodles
Flat/Wide Noodles
Egg Noodles
Noodle Type
Thickness
Straight Noodles
Curly Noodles
Flat/Wide Noodles
Egg Noodles
Noodle Type
Thickness
Straight Noodles
Curly Noodles
Flat/Wide Noodles
Egg Noodles
Noodle Type
Thickness
Straight Noodles
Curly Noodles
Flat/Wide Noodles
Egg Noodles
Noodle Type
Thickness
Straight Noodles
Curly Noodles
Flat/Wide Noodles
Egg Noodles
Noodle Type
Thickness
Straight Noodles
Curly Noodles
Flat/Wide Noodles
Egg Noodles
Noodle Type
Thickness
Straight Noodles
Curly Noodles
Flat/Wide Noodles
Egg Noodles
Noodle Type
Thickness
Straight Noodles
Curly Noodles
Flat/Wide Noodles
Egg Noodles
Noodle Type
Thickness
Straight Noodles
Curly Noodles
Flat/Wide Noodles
Egg Noodles
Noodle Type
Thickness
Straight Noodles
Curly Noodles
Flat/Wide Noodles
Egg Noodles
Noodle Type
Thickness
Straight Noodles
Curly Noodles
Flat/Wide Noodles
Egg Noodles
Noodle Type
Thickness
Straight Noodles
Curly Noodles
Flat/Wide Noodles
Egg Noodles
Noodle Type
Thickness
Straight Noodles
Curly Noodles
Flat/Wide Noodles
Egg Noodles
Noodle Type
Thickness
Straight Noodles
Curly Noodles
Flat/Wide Noodles
Egg Noodles
Noodle Type
Thickness
Straight Noodles
Curly Noodles
Flat/Wide Noodles
Egg Noodles
Noodle Type
Thickness
Straight Noodles
Curly Noodles
Flat/Wide Noodles
Egg Noodles
Noodle Type
Thickness
Straight Noodles
Curly Noodles
Flat/Wide Noodles
Egg Noodles
Noodle Type
Thickness
Straight Noodles
Curly Noodles
Flat/Wide Noodles
Egg Noodles
Noodle Type
Thickness
Straight Noodles
Curly Noodles
Flat/Wide Noodles
Egg Noodles
Noodle Type
Thickness
Straight Noodles
Curly Noodles
Flat/Wide Noodles
Egg Noodles
Noodle Type
Thickness
Straight Noodles
Curly Noodles
Flat/Wide Noodles
Egg Noodles
Noodle Type
Thickness
Straight Noodles
Curly Noodles
Flat/Wide Noodles
Egg Noodles
Noodle Type
Thickness
Straight Noodles
Curly Noodles
Flat/Wide Noodles
Egg Noodles
Noodle Type
Thickness
Straight Noodles
Curly Noodles
Flat/Wide Noodles
Egg Noodles
Noodle Type
Thickness
Straight Noodles
Curly Noodles
Flat/Wide Noodles
Egg Noodles
Noodle Type
Thickness
Straight Noodles
Curly Noodles
Flat/Wide Noodles
Egg Noodles
Noodle Type
Thickness
Straight Noodles
Curly Noodles
Flat/Wide Noodles
Egg Noodles
Noodle Type
Thickness
Straight Noodles
Curly Noodles
Flat/Wide Noodles
Egg Noodles
Noodle Type
Thickness
Straight Noodles
Curly Noodles
Flat/Wide Noodles
Egg Noodles
Noodle Type
Thickness
Straight Noodles
Curly Noodles
Flat/Wide Noodles
Egg Noodles
Noodle Type
Thickness
Straight Noodles
Curly Noodles
Flat/Wide Noodles
Egg Noodles
Choose which type of noodles you want before the day's end, and let us—
この中から種類を選択して
日付が変わるまでに連絡…
Noodle Type
Thickness
Straight Noodles
Curly Noodles
Flat/Wide Noodles
Egg Noodles
Noodle Type
Thickness
Straight Noodles
Curly Noodles
Flat/Wide Noodles
Egg Noodles
Noodle Type
Thickness
Straight Noodles
Curly Noodles
Flat/Wide Noodles
Egg Noodles
Noodle Type
Thickness
Straight Noodles
Curly Noodles
Flat/Wide Noodles
Egg Noodles
Thickness
Straight Noodles
Noodle Type
Curly Noodles
Flat/Wide Noodles
Egg Noodles
Noodle Type
Curly Noodles
Flat/Wide Noodles
Egg Noodles
Thickness
Straight Noodles
I'll choose this one from wide noodles.
（黒木場）
俺は この… 幅広タイプの麺で
Are you sure that's your final choice?
もう決定でいいのかい？
It'll be fine.
（黒木場）大丈夫っす
I already know what kind
of ramen I'll be making.
どんなラーメンにするか
もう頭の中で固まったんで
He figured that out just now?
（ドアを開ける音）
（恵）今の一瞬で？
（ドアを閉める音）
（恵）ああ…
Tadokoro-chan, there's no need to rush.
あ… 田所ちゃん
焦ることはないよ
You just need to tell us by midnight.
今夜12時までに
知らせてくれればいい
O-Okay.
あ… はい！
（恵）
麺を運営側が
用意してくれるっていうのは―
Since the organizers will prepare the noodles,
maybe that means they want us
to focus on the broth.
スープの味作りに
専念しろってことなのかも
Let's Make Ramen
An Introduction to the Art
Make ramen served at famous shops!
Recipes
Tadokoro Megumi
Let's Make Ramen
An Introduction to the Art
Make ramen served at famous shops!
Recipes
Tadokoro Megumi
Let's Make Ramen
An Introduction to the Art
Make ramen served at famous shops!
Recipes
Tadokoro Megumi
Let's Make Ramen
An Introduction to the Art
Make ramen served at famous shops!
Recipes
Tadokoro Megumi
Let's Make Ramen
An Introduction to the Art
Make ramen served at famous shops!
Recipes
Tadokoro Megumi
Let's Make Ramen
An Introduction to the Art
Make ramen served at famous shops!
Recipes
Tadokoro Megumi
Let's Make Ramen
An Introduction to the Art
Make ramen served at famous shops!
Recipes
Tadokoro Megumi
Let's Make Ramen
An Introduction to the Art
Make ramen served at famous shops!
Recipes
Tadokoro Megumi
Let's Make Ramen
An Introduction to the Art
Make ramen served at famous shops!
Recipes
Tadokoro Megumi
Let's Make Ramen
An Introduction to the Art
Make ramen served at famous shops!
Recipes
Tadokoro Megumi
Let's Make Ramen
An Introduction to the Art
Make ramen served at famous shops!
Recipes
Tadokoro Megumi
Let's Make Ramen
An Introduction to the Art
Make ramen served at famous shops!
Recipes
Tadokoro Megumi
Let's Make Ramen
An Introduction to the Art
Make ramen served at famous shops!
Recipes
Tadokoro Megumi
Let's Make Ramen
An Introduction to the Art
Make ramen served at famous shops!
Recipes
Tadokoro Megumi
Let's Make Ramen
An Introduction to the Art
Make ramen served at famous shops!
Recipes
Tadokoro Megumi
Let's Make Ramen
An Introduction to the Art
Make ramen served at famous shops!
Recipes
Tadokoro Megumi
Let's Make Ramen
An Introduction to the Art
Make ramen served at famous shops!
Recipes
Tadokoro Megumi
Let's Make Ramen
An Introduction to the Art
Make ramen served at famous shops!
Recipes
Tadokoro Megumi
Let's Make Ramen
An Introduction to the Art
Make ramen served at famous shops!
Recipes
Tadokoro Megumi
Let's Make Ramen
An Introduction to the Art
Make ramen served at famous shops!
Recipes
Tadokoro Megumi
Let's Make Ramen
An Introduction to the Art
Make ramen served at famous shops!
Recipes
Tadokoro Megumi
Let's Make Ramen
An Introduction to the Art
Make ramen served at famous shops!
Recipes
Tadokoro Megumi
Let's Make Ramen
An Introduction to the Art
Make ramen served at famous shops!
Recipes
Tadokoro Megumi
Let's Make Ramen
An Introduction to the Art
Make ramen served at famous shops!
Recipes
Tadokoro Megumi
Let's Make Ramen
An Introduction to the Art
Make ramen served at famous shops!
Recipes
Tadokoro Megumi
Let's Make Ramen
An Introduction to the Art
Make ramen served at famous shops!
Recipes
Tadokoro Megumi
Let's Make Ramen
An Introduction to the Art
Make ramen served at famous shops!
Recipes
Tadokoro Megumi
Let's Make Ramen
An Introduction to the Art
Make ramen served at famous shops!
Recipes
Tadokoro Megumi
Let's Make Ramen
An Introduction to the Art
Make ramen served at famous shops!
Recipes
Tadokoro Megumi
Let's Make Ramen
An Introduction to the Art
Make ramen served at famous shops!
Recipes
Tadokoro Megumi
Let's Make Ramen
An Introduction to the Art
Make ramen served at famous shops!
Recipes
Tadokoro Megumi
Let's Make Ramen
An Introduction to the Art
Make ramen served at famous shops!
Recipes
Tadokoro Megumi
Let's Make Ramen
An Introduction to the Art
Make ramen served at famous shops!
Recipes
Tadokoro Megumi
Let's Make Ramen
An Introduction to the Art
Make ramen served at famous shops!
Recipes
Tadokoro Megumi
Let's Make Ramen
An Introduction to the Art
Make ramen served at famous shops!
Recipes
Tadokoro Megumi
Let's Make Ramen
An Introduction to the Art
Make ramen served at famous shops!
Recipes
Tadokoro Megumi
Let's Make Ramen
An Introduction to the Art
Make ramen served at famous shops!
Recipes
Tadokoro Megumi
Let's Make Ramen
An Introduction to the Art
Make ramen served at famous shops!
Recipes
Tadokoro Megumi
Let's Make Ramen
An Introduction to the Art
Make ramen served at famous shops!
Recipes
Tadokoro Megumi
Let's Make Ramen
An Introduction to the Art
Make ramen served at famous shops!
Recipes
Tadokoro Megumi
Let's Make Ramen
An Introduction to the Art
Make ramen served at famous shops!
Recipes
Tadokoro Megumi
Let's Make Ramen
An Introduction to the Art
Make ramen served at famous shops!
Recipes
Tadokoro Megumi
Let's Make Ramen
An Introduction to the Art
Make ramen served at famous shops!
Recipes
Tadokoro Megumi
Let's Make Ramen
An Introduction to the Art
Make ramen served at famous shops!
Recipes
Tadokoro Megumi
Let's Make Ramen
An Introduction to the Art
Make ramen served at famous shops!
Recipes
Tadokoro Megumi
Let's Make Ramen
An Introduction to the Art
Make ramen served at famous shops!
Recipes
Tadokoro Megumi
Let's Make Ramen
An Introduction to the Art
Make ramen served at famous shops!
Recipes
Tadokoro Megumi
Let's Make Ramen
An Introduction to the Art
Make ramen served at famous shops!
Recipes
Tadokoro Megumi
Let's Make Ramen
An Introduction to the Art
Make ramen served at famous shops!
Recipes
Tadokoro Megumi
Let's Make Ramen
An Introduction to the Art
Make ramen served at famous shops!
Recipes
Tadokoro Megumi
Let's Make Ramen
An Introduction to the Art
Make ramen served at famous shops!
Recipes
Tadokoro Megumi
Let's Make Ramen
An Introduction to the Art
Make ramen served at famous shops!
Recipes
Tadokoro Megumi
Let's Make Ramen
An Introduction to the Art
Make ramen served at famous shops!
Recipes
Tadokoro Megumi
Let's Make Ramen
An Introduction to the Art
Make ramen served at famous shops!
Recipes
Tadokoro Megumi
Let's Make Ramen
An Introduction to the Art
Make ramen served at famous shops!
Recipes
Tadokoro Megumi
Let's Make Ramen
An Introduction to the Art
Make ramen served at famous shops!
Recipes
Tadokoro Megumi
Let's Make Ramen
An Introduction to the Art
Make ramen served at famous shops!
Recipes
Tadokoro Megumi
Let's Make Ramen
An Introduction to the Art
Make ramen served at famous shops!
Recipes
Tadokoro Megumi
Let's Make Ramen
An Introduction to the Art
Make ramen served at famous shops!
Recipes
Tadokoro Megumi
Let's Make Ramen
An Introduction to the Art
Make ramen served at famous shops!
Recipes
Tadokoro Megumi
Let's Make Ramen
An Introduction to the Art
Make ramen served at famous shops!
Recipes
Tadokoro Megumi
Let's Make Ramen
An Introduction to the Art
Make ramen served at famous shops!
Recipes
Tadokoro Megumi
Let's Make Ramen
An Introduction to the Art
Make ramen served at famous shops!
Recipes
Tadokoro Megumi
Let's Make Ramen
An Introduction to the Art
Make ramen served at famous shops!
Recipes
Tadokoro Megumi
Let's Make Ramen
An Introduction to the Art
Make ramen served at famous shops!
Recipes
Tadokoro Megumi
Let's Make Ramen
An Introduction to the Art
Make ramen served at famous shops!
Recipes
Tadokoro Megumi
Let's Make Ramen
An Introduction to the Art
Make ramen served at famous shops!
Recipes
Tadokoro Megumi
Let's Make Ramen
An Introduction to the Art
Make ramen served at famous shops!
Recipes
Tadokoro Megumi
Let's Make Ramen
An Introduction to the Art
Make ramen served at famous shops!
Recipes
Tadokoro Megumi
Let's Make Ramen
An Introduction to the Art
Make ramen served at famous shops!
Recipes
Tadokoro Megumi
Let's Make Ramen
An Introduction to the Art
Make ramen served at famous shops!
Recipes
Tadokoro Megumi
Let's Make Ramen
An Introduction to the Art
Make ramen served at famous shops!
Recipes
Tadokoro Megumi
Let's Make Ramen
An Introduction to the Art
Make ramen served at famous shops!
Recipes
Tadokoro Megumi
Let's Make Ramen
An Introduction to the Art
Make ramen served at famous shops!
Recipes
Tadokoro Megumi
Let's Make Ramen
An Introduction to the Art
Make ramen served at famous shops!
Recipes
Tadokoro Megumi
Let's Make Ramen
An Introduction to the Art
Make ramen served at famous shops!
Recipes
Tadokoro Megumi
Let's Make Ramen
An Introduction to the Art
Make ramen served at famous shops!
Recipes
Tadokoro Megumi
Let's Make Ramen
An Introduction to the Art
Make ramen served at famous shops!
Recipes
Tadokoro Megumi
Let's Make Ramen
An Introduction to the Art
Make ramen served at famous shops!
Recipes
Tadokoro Megumi
Let's Make Ramen
An Introduction to the Art
Make ramen served at famous shops!
Recipes
Tadokoro Megumi
Let's Make Ramen
An Introduction to the Art
Make ramen served at famous shops!
Recipes
Tadokoro Megumi
Let's Make Ramen
An Introduction to the Art
Make ramen served at famous shops!
Recipes
Tadokoro Megumi
Let's Make Ramen
An Introduction to the Art
Make ramen served at famous shops!
Recipes
Tadokoro Megumi
The broth is created by its base made of stock,
the concentrated sauce known as kaeshi,
ラーメンのスープを構成してるのは
ベースになる だし
“かえし”とも呼ばれるタレ
along with various
infused oils and spices.
そして各種の香味油や香辛料
If those components fail to complement each other,
the flavor will be fragmented.
それが全部かみ合わないと
味はバラバラになる
The noodles Kurokiba-kun selected have an oval cross-section with a notable elasticity.
黒木場君が選んだ麺
弾むような弾力が特徴の
楕円形(だえんけい)のもの
Wide noodles are typically paired
with rich, strong flavors.
幅広の麺は コクのある濃い味と
合わせるのが定石
Maybe that means Kurokiba-kun intends to make a very rich broth.
ていうことは 黒木場君は
濃厚なスープを作るつもりなのかな
To counter that, should I also make broth with an equally strong flavor?
対抗するには 私も
それに負けないような強い味を？
First things first. I have to start testing!
とにかく試作を進めなきゃ！
It's no good!
ダメだぁ…
When I try to make a rich broth,
the flavors don't come together.
濃厚なスープにしようとすると
味がまとまらないよぉ…
What should I do?
ああ 一体どうしたら？
Megumi!
（大御堂(だいみどう)ふみ緒(お)）
恵　あんた宛ての荷物
You have a package from your home.
（恵）あ…
（ふみ緒）実家からだよ
What?
ああっ
Megumi,
（恵の母）〝恵へ〞
〝秋の選抜本戦への出場
おめでとう〞
congratulations on proceeding to the main tournament of the Autumn Elections.
Though I can't come cheer
you on because of work,
“仕事があるから
応援には行けないけど―”
“頑張ってね”
I wish you the best of luck.
“地元の食材を送ります”
I'm sending you ingredients from home.
Mom...
お母さん…
Dried Squid
Shiitake
Iriko
Wow, all of this brings back memories.
Dried Squid
Shiitake
Iriko
Dried Squid
Shiitake
Iriko
Dried Squid
Shiitake
Iriko
Dried Squid
Shiitake
Iriko
Dried Squid
Shiitake
Iriko
Dried Squid
Shiitake
Iriko
Dried Squid
Shiitake
Iriko
Dried Squid
Shiitake
Iriko
うわ 懐かしいなぁ
Dried Squid
Shiitake
Iriko
Dried Squid
Shiitake
Iriko
Dried Squid
Shiitake
Iriko
Dried Squid
Shiitake
Iriko
Dried Squid
Shiitake
Iriko
Dried Squid
Shiitake
Iriko
Dried Squid
Shiitake
Iriko
Dried Squid
Shiitake
Iriko
Dried Squid
Shiitake
Iriko
Dried Squid
Shiitake
Iriko
Dried Squid
Shiitake
Iriko
Dried Squid
Shiitake
Iriko
Dried Squid
Shiitake
Iriko
Dried Squid
Shiitake
Iriko
Dried Squid
Shiitake
Iriko
Dried Squid
Shiitake
Iriko
Dried Squid
Shiitake
Iriko
Dried Squid
Shiitake
Iriko
Dried Squid
Shiitake
Iriko
Dried Squid
Shiitake
Iriko
Dried Squid
Shiitake
Iriko
Dried Squid
Shiitake
Iriko
Dried Squid
Shiitake
Iriko
Dried Squid
Shiitake
Iriko
Dried Squid
Shiitake
Iriko
Dried Squid
Shiitake
Iriko
Dried Squid
Shiitake
Iriko
Dried Squid
Shiitake
Iriko
Dried Squid
Shiitake
Iriko
Dried Squid
Shiitake
Iriko
Dried Squid
Shiitake
Iriko
Dried Squid
Shiitake
Iriko
Dried Squid
Shiitake
Iriko
Dried Squid
Shiitake
Iriko
Dried Squid
Shiitake
Iriko
Dried Squid
Shiitake
Iriko
Dried Squid
Shiitake
Iriko
Dried Squid
Shiitake
Iriko
Dried Squid
Shiitake
Iriko
Dried Squid
Shiitake
Iriko
Dried Squid
Shiitake
Iriko
Dried Squid
Shiitake
Iriko
Dried Squid
Shiitake
Iriko
Dried Squid
Shiitake
Iriko
Dried Squid
Shiitake
Iriko
Dried Squid
Shiitake
Iriko
Dried Squid
Shiitake
Iriko
Dried Squid
Shiitake
Iriko
Dried Squid
Shiitake
Iriko
Dried Squid
Shiitake
Iriko
Dried Squid
Shiitake
Iriko
Dried Squid
Shiitake
Iriko
Dried Squid
Shiitake
Iriko
Dried Squid
Shiitake
Iriko
Dried Squid
Shiitake
Iriko
Dried Squid
Shiitake
Iriko
Dried Squid
Shiitake
Iriko
Dried Squid
Shiitake
Iriko
Dried Squid
Shiitake
Iriko
Dried Squid
Shiitake
Iriko
Dried Squid
Shiitake
Iriko
地元で よく使ってた食材が
たくさん！
Dried Squid
Shiitake
Iriko
So many ingredients
I used to cook with back home!
Dried Squid
Shiitake
Iriko
Dried Squid
Shiitake
Iriko
Dried Squid
Shiitake
Iriko
Dried Squid
Shiitake
Iriko
Dried Squid
Shiitake
Iriko
Dried Squid
Shiitake
Iriko
Dried Squid
Shiitake
Iriko
Dried Squid
Shiitake
Iriko
Dried Squid
Shiitake
Iriko
Dried Squid
Shiitake
Iriko
Dried Squid
Shiitake
Iriko
Dried Squid
Shiitake
Iriko
Dried Squid
Shiitake
Iriko
Dried Squid
Shiitake
Iriko
Dried Squid
Shiitake
Iriko
Dried Squid
Shiitake
Iriko
Dried Squid
Shiitake
Iriko
Dried Squid
Shiitake
Iriko
Dried Squid
Shiitake
Iriko
Dried Squid
Shiitake
Iriko
Dried Squid
Shiitake
Iriko
Dried Squid
Shiitake
Iriko
Dried Squid
Shiitake
Iriko
Dried Squid
Shiitake
Iriko
Dried Squid
Shiitake
Iriko
Dried Squid
Shiitake
Iriko
Dried Squid
Shiitake
Iriko
Dried Squid
Shiitake
Iriko
Dried Squid
Shiitake
Iriko
Dried Squid
Shiitake
Iriko
Dried Squid
Shiitake
Iriko
Dried Squid
Shiitake
Iriko
Dried Squid
Shiitake
Iriko
Dried Squid
Shiitake
Iriko
Dried Squid
Shiitake
Iriko
Dried Squid
Shiitake
Iriko
Dried Squid
Shiitake
Iriko
Dried Squid
Shiitake
Iriko
Dried Squid
Shiitake
Iriko
Dried Squid
Shiitake
Iriko
Dried Squid
Shiitake
Iriko
あっ
I'll use the ingredients
my mom sent me in the match!
私はお母さんが送ってくれた食材で
勝負する！
Um...
（創真）えっと…
お…
MEGUMI
LOVE
That spot's got a weird splashy vibe going on.
（創真）
あそこだけ異様な華やかさだな
Oh, Yukihira, over here!
お！　幸平～ こっちだよ～
MEGUMI
LOVE
Why do they write names on fans, Bro?
（イサミ･アルディーニ）
どうして うちわに名前を
書くんだろうね 兄ちゃん
MEGUMI
LOVE
（タクミ･アルディーニ）
日本の神秘だな
MEGUMI
LOVE
It's one of Japan's mysteries.
MEGUMI
LOVE
Hm...
（大泉柿之進(おおいずみかきのしん)）ふ～む　ラーメン
Ramen.
It is a dish comprised of three components:
noodles, toppings, and soup.
すなわち麺 トッピング そして
スープの３要素で構成される麺料理
You just keep the challenging topics coming year after year, don't you?
また今年は無理難題を
吹っかけたものですなぁ
Indeed.
（仙左衛門）フン…
Ramen enjoyed an explosive popularity after the war, during the recovery period.
ラーメンは戦後の復興期に
爆発的に広まった
The popularity was due to their affordable taste
and the ease of access, thanks to noodle carts.
安価で美味な上に―
RAMEN
屋台によって
手軽に提供できたからだ
（えりな）
今やラーメンは
世界に発信される日本食となった
And now, ramen has become a Japanese cuisine that has gone global.
There's limitless potential for the depth of flavor and amount of effort spent preparing it.
味の奥深さや かかる手間も
計り知れない
And we're asking contestants to perfect it all in a single night,
それをたった一晩でやれと言う
それも この大舞台でだ
on such a big stage!
In essence, what is being tested in this match
すなわち この勝負で試されるのは
柔軟性と瞬発力
is flexibility and explosive power!
How well can they bring the experience and aptitude that they've nurtured thus far to bear on the topic at hand?
培ってきた経験値
自分の力を
どこまでお題に生かせるか
Kurokiba Ryou made seafood
curry in the preliminaries.
（丸井善二(まるいぜんじ)）
予選で黒木場リョウが出したのは
海鮮カレーだったが―
I wonder what he's making
for the main tournament.
本戦では どんな品で
くるんだろうな
That broth is based on stock taken entirely from fish heads and bones!
（郁魅）
あのスープ 全部
魚のあらから だしをとってる
Scorpionfish, conger eel,
flounder, and red gurnard.
（榊涼子(さかきりょうこ)）
カサゴやアナゴ
ヒラメにホウボウ
魚介ベースのラーメンになるのね
So the ramen will have a seafood broth!
A-ha!
どぅは～！
All the strong flavors of fish guts
and shrimp innards.
魚の内臓やエビみその強烈な風味
（審査員Ｂ）
臭みを出さず
見事に処理してるようだなぁ
It seems he has been able to avoid any fishiness thus far! Well done.
Like I thought, Kurokiba-kun is making a rich broth from seafood.
（恵）
やっぱり黒木場君は
魚介系の濃厚スープを…
Scallops!
（涼子）
ホタテだわ　恵はホタテ貝柱の
乾物で だしをとってる
MEGUMI
LOVE
Megumi is using dried scallops to make her stock.
MEGUMI
LOVE
（恵）
このだしに あく抜きした
白湯(ぱいたん)スープを合わせて―
Add strained paitan soup to the stock...
and simmer the broth!
さらに煮込んでいく！
LOVE
MEGUMI
Wait. So Megumi's also making a seafood broth?
LOVE
MEGUMI
てことは 恵も魚介系のスープで
いくつもりなの？
LOVE
MEGUMI
No, they may both be using seafood,
LOVE
MEGUMI
いや
同じ魚介系スープではあるけど―
LOVE
MEGUMI
黒木場リョウの
濃厚スープに対し―
but in contrast to Kurokiba Ryou's rich broth,
Tadokoro-san chose a light broth.
田所さんは
淡麗スープを選択したんだ
But can her broth compete against the impact of Kurokiba's rich broth?
だが それで黒木場の濃厚スープの
インパクトに張り合えるのか？
Of course it can!
MEGUMI
Love
そうだよ！
恵の実家は港町だもん
Megumi's hometown is a harbor town!
I doubt he knows more
about seafood than she does!
海産物への理解なら
絶対負けないはずだよ！
（アリス）
ウフッ　面白いわね
港町育ち対決だなんて
Very interesting.
Two people who grew up in
harbor towns against each other.
MEGUMI
Love
Right, a fishing port...
そうそう　漁港の…
MEGUMI
Love
（悠姫）ううっ？
（創真）ん？
What?!
MEGUMI
Love
（悠姫）ううっ？
（創真）ん？
（アリス）ウッフ
Nakiri Alice?!
薙切アリス！
Wh-Why are you here?!
なあっ？　何でいるのぉ？
Huh? Am I not allowed?
あ～ら いけない？
You said they're both from harbor towns?
“港町育ち対決”って
言ったか？
That's right!
そうよ　リョウ君は
海と共に育ったんだもの
Ryou-kun grew up next to the sea.
（郁魅）
大量のオマールエビと
甘エビの殻？
A huge pile of lobster
and sweet shrimp shells?
Is he going to use them for stock too?
あれも だしに使うのか？
ええい！
えいえいえい
ええええええええい！
ええええええええ！
What the hell?!
（男子生徒Ａ）何だ？
He's crushing the shells into powder!
（男子生徒Ｂ）
殻を粉々に砕いてる？
10 YEARS AGO
There's a place that's popular in the sailors' watering hole district.
（研究員Ａ）
船乗りたちが
集まる酒場町に―
にぎわってる店が
あるらしいな
Really? I want to check it out.
（研究員Ｂ）
へえ 行ってみたいもんだな
（研究員Ｃ）
ハハハッ　やめとけ
荒くれ野郎に身ぐるみ剥がされるぞ
I'd advise against it!
You'll lose everything you have to a savage!
（カモメの鳴き声）
Now that I've finally left Japan,
（アリス）
せっかく日本を離れたんですもの
貪欲(どんよく)にいろんな味を経験しなくちゃ
I should try to experience
lots of different flavors.
This must be the place.
ここね
（ドアの開く音）
あ…
What, a customer?
何だよ 客か？
The place is on break right now.
今は休憩時間だ
飯なら よそ…
Get your food somewhere else—
じゃあ
店内で待たせてもらうわね
Then I'll just wait inside!
わあ～ 汚いお店！
Wow, it's so dirty in here!
I know! Since I'm here,
can you introduce me to the chef?
そうだ　せっかくだから
シェフにあいさつさせてくださる？
（アリス）あっ…
（黒木場）勝手なことはさせねえ
You won't get to do as you please here.
The chef of this place...
この店のシェフは―
is me.
俺だ
えっ？
What?
A chef?
（創真）シェフ？
That's right.
そう　リョウ君は幼い頃から
調理場のトップに立っていた
Ryou-kun has been the head chef
since he was very young.
That's the kind of chef he is.
そういう料理人なのよ
MEGUMI
M-Megumi's the same way!
め… 恵だって―
MEGUMI
Love
She has the experience of helping out at her kitchen back home too!
実家の厨房(ちゅうぼう)を手伝ってた経験を
持ってるじゃんかぁ！
Polar Star
Megumi!
めぇぐみー！
気持ちで負けちゃダメだよー！
Polar Star
Don't let any of this get to you!
私たちが ついてるからねー！
Polar Star
We've got your back!
（黒木場）ん？
（恵）わぁ… へへ…
What the hell's that?
（黒木場）何だ ありゃ
え… えーと
私の住んでる寮の友達で…
O-Oh, they're friends from my dorm.
ううー… 気に入らねえな
I don't like this at all.
I feel sick to my stomach whenever
I see a bunch of chefs palling around.
ぬくぬくと なれ合ってる
料理人連中を見てると―
ヘドが出る
Chefs are all about winning or being beaten.
料理人同士の関係は
食うか食われるか
There can be nothing else!
それ以外に ありはしねえ
Are you... sure about that?
そう… なのかな？
What?
（黒木場）ああ？
（恵）料理っていうのは みんなで
協力し合うことも大事なんじゃ…
Isn't it important for people to work together in cooking too?
厨房は戦場　料理は力だ！
The kitchen is a battlefield.
Cooking is about power!
You wouldn't understand because you were sheltered as a kid.
ぬるま湯で育ってきた奴には
分からねえだろうがな
All your cooking needs to do is to bring your opponents to their knees.
（黒木場）
料理に必要なのは
相手を屈服させること それだけだ
That's it.
それを分かってねえ連中には
腑抜けた味しか作れねえ
People who don't get that can only make food with weak flavor!
Get that through your thick skull!
理解しとけ
The cooking the rest of you have been doing is just trash—a game of pretend.
お前らが やってきた料理は
ゴミみたいなお遊びなんだよ
（恵）え…
You're wrong.
（恵）違うよ
（黒木場）ああ？
What I...
私が… 少なくとも
私が出会ってきたものは…
At least, what I've encountered is...
（タイマーの音）
nothing like trash!
ゴミなんかじゃないよ！
The vegetables have been parboiled.
野菜の下ゆで完了
２種類の しょうゆを合わせて―
Mix two types of soy sauce together,
then keep the temperature around 80 degrees Celsius to preserve the flavor.
しょうゆの風味を飛ばさないように
火入れは80度前後をキープ
All right!
よし！
（伊武崎峻(いぶさきしゅん)）
いいぞ　落ち着いてる
Good. She's staying calm.
Yup.
ああ　１つ１つの作業を
きっちりさばいて 無駄がねえ
She's getting each task done
without wasting any time.
What determines ramen's flavor is the stock.
（えりな）
ラーメンの味を決めるのは
やはり だし
There can be no cloudiness in the light broth she chose for her dish.
彼女が選択した淡麗系のスープは
一点の濁りすら許されない
（観客のどよめき）
Beautiful.
美しいな
It shines, and it is crystal clear.
輝きながら澄んでいる
（２人）おお～
（２人）おお！
Don't say bad things about
the people who have...
（恵）
私の背中を押してくれた
みんなのことを―
encouraged me!
悪く言わないで！
うううー…
That was just me...
trying to say something!
なーんて言ってみたり…
Okay, it's close to the time limit!
（麗）
さあ 制限時間が近づいています
Who will finish first?
先に完成するのは
どちらでしょうか
All right!
（恵）よし！
（男子生徒Ｃ）おお！　何だぁ？
Whoa, what?
Look at the judges...
（恵）あ…
（男子生徒Ｃ）審査員たちが…
What's about to start?
（女子生徒Ａ）何が始まるの？
Well, watching the chef work
at the counter in a ramen shop
なに カウンターで
店主の仕事ぶりを見物するのも―
is one of the pleasures of ramen.
ラーメンの だいご味の
１つだからのう
C-Cooking right in front
of the Devil of Food?
（丸井）
ちょっ… “食の魔王”の目の前で
調理するなんて…
Hey!
ちょっとぉ　恵のプレッシャーに
なるようなことしないでよぉ～
Don't pressure Megumi!
Don't worry. She's staying calm.
大丈夫　冷静だわ
（大泉）
おお～！　近くで見るとまた美しく
香りも素晴らしい
It's even more beautiful
and fragrant up close!
The toppings seem to be mostly vegetables.
（早乙女星周(さおとめせいしゅう)）
トッピングは野菜がメインかぁ
This looks promising.
（審査員Ａ）
これは期待できそうですな
I think things are going her way.
（伊武崎）いい空気だ
（涼子）うん
Yeah.
MEGUMI
LOVE
Okay, Megumi!
よーし 恵ぃ
そのまま勝っちゃえー！
MEGUMI
LOVE
Barrel right along to a win!
MEGUMI
LOVE
（涼子）あっ
（観客）おおっ
（黒木場）ええいっ！
That's right. That's Ryou-kun right there.
そう これがリョウ君
You...
（黒木場）お前 見ない顔だな
You're not from around here.
Don't be so rude!
お前だなんて失礼ね！
I have a name—I'm Alice!
私にはアリスという名前が
あります
Uh-huh.
（黒木場）あっそ
You should tell me your name too!
あなたも名乗りなさいよね！
Ryou.
リョウ
Ryou?
リョウ？
ファミリーネームは？
What's your family name?
Kurokiba.
黒木場
ふうん
Oh, it sounds kind of Japanese.
何だか日本ぽい名前だわ
So. You'd better have money
to pay for the food.
で 飯代はあるんだろうな？
Of course I do.
（アリス）もちろんよ
（黒木場）ならいい
That's fine, then.
（客Ａ）ああ 腹減ったなぁ
Man, I'm starving.
What should I eat today?
（客Ｂ）今日は何食うかな
The regulars are showing up.
（黒木場）常連が集まってきたか
There's still time until we open for dinner,
ディナーの開店時間までは
少しあるが―
but I guess it's okay. Let's do this.
まあいい　やるか
（アリス）ん？
What?
何？
（黒木場）ええい…
（アリス）空気が… 変わった？
He's... changed!
Line up!
並べっ！
Pay for your meal and follow my orders.
料理の代金を支払うこと
俺の命令に従うこと
If you can do those two things, I'll serve you food.
この２つを守るなら俺の客だ
I'll open up the place!
開店するぞ！
（客たち）うおおおお！
Too slow!
（黒木場）遅(おせ)えんだよ！
I told you to prioritize prep work
and stuffing the chicken!
下ごしらえはチキンの詰め物から
優先しろって言っただろうが！
It's because you tried to multitask without
having the skills to do it that you fall behind!
技術もねえのに
同時にさばこうとするから―
そうやって手が遅れるんだよ！
（料理人）う… うう…
Forget it.
もういい　てめえらは
注文を取りに行きやがれ！
You guys can just go take orders from customers!
うっ　くっ…
I can't stand it anymore!
（料理人）もう我慢ならねえ！
What's with your attitude?!
何なんだ その態度は！
Don't you dare think you're better than adults!
大人をナメてんじゃねえぞ
こらぁ！
Oh, yeah?
だったら てめえ―
Are you saying you can put better food on the table than me?
俺より うまい飯が
出せるのかよ？
（料理人）うう…
I can fill your spot just fine
all by myself if I have to.
（黒木場）
てめえ１人の穴ぐらい―
俺がいりゃあ
どうとでもなるからな
ええい…
I'm sorry, Chef.
…申し訳ありません シェフ
Here it comes!
（客Ｃ）うっひょ～！　来た来たぁ
It's the best!
（客Ｄ）最高だぜ！
I can't leave land without
having eaten Ryou's food!
（客Ｅ）リョウの飯を食わないで
陸(おか)を離れるなんて考えられねえ
ンフッ
Candidate Kurokiba seems to have finished first!
（麗）
先に完成したのは
黒木場選手のようです
Hey, what is that?
（男子生徒Ｄ）おい あれ 何だ？
What's on top?
（男子生徒Ｅ）何を乗せてる？
Wait a minute. Is that rusk?
（男子生徒Ｆ）
ひょっとして ラスク？
Go on. Dig in.
さあ 食ってくれ
It's Soupe de Poisson Ramen!
スープ･ド･ポワソン･ラーメンだ
Soupe de Poisson...
スープ･ド･ポワソン
It's a southern French soup based on stock made from fish heads, bones, and the shells of shellfish.
魚のあらや殻のだしで作る
南フランスのスープ
He adapted it into ramen?
それをラーメンに応用したのか
First...
では まずスープから
let's try the soup.
うわあ！
The innards of shrimp
and fish form a rich, cohesive taste.
エビみそや魚の内臓
全てのコクが混然一体となって―
What ferocious flavor!
なんと荒々しい味なのだ…
Allow me to tangle these noodles
into the soup and try them!
このスープを麺に絡めて いざ！
Oh, God!
うわあ！　ああ いかん
意識を持っていかれる
It's making me feel faint!
旨味の暴力！
The umami is so violent!
The toppings consist of three types of cheese,
（審査員Ｂ）
トッピングは３種のチーズ
rouille made from aioli sauce
with added chili peppers,
アイオリソースに
トウガラシを加えたルイユ
and tempura batter bits acting as crouton stand-ins!
クルトンの役割を果たす天かす
そして先ほどのラスク
And there's the rusk we saw earlier!
It's been smeared with Echire butter,
then toasted golden brown.
エシレバターを塗り
じっくり焼いてある
あむっ
でやあ！　そうかぁ！
I see!
He was crushing dried shells
containing concentrated flavor!
奴が砕いていたのは 乾燥させ
風味を倍増させた殻だったのかぁ！
So you've finally realized what's going on.
やっと気づいたか
That crushed powder is everywhere in this ramen,
from the soup stock to the butter on the rusk!
このラーメンには
スープのだしからバターにまで―
そのパウダーを
たっぷりと仕込んである
The umami factors in shrimp are glycine, algine, and proline.
エビの旨味エキスは―
グリシン アルギニン
プロリンだけど―
Crustaceans have the highest concentration of those factors among all seafood.
甲殻類は 魚介でトップの含有率を
持っているの
He pulverized shells containing all that umami and used the powder directly in the dish,
そのエキスをたっぷり含んだ
殻の粉末を―
そのまま投入してるんだから
強烈なおいしさも必然だわ
so of course the result is incredibly delicious.
（審査員たち）
うんうん むしゃむしゃ
（大泉）うんんん…
I see.
（仙左衛門）なるほど
暴力的なまでのおいしさ
It's so flavorful that it's almost violently so.
この男にとって
料理を食わすことは…
For this man, having others eat his food...
食ええええ…
is like an all-out fistfight.
（仙左衛門）
殴り合いのケンカそのもの
He's spent his whole life
making everyone concede defeat.
こうやって全てを屈服させ
生きてきたのか
（黒木場）
いつまで気取ってやがる ジジイ
How long are you gonna keep putting on your airs, old man?
It's just you and me now.
タイマンだ！
Very well!
よかろう！
ええい！
てえああ！
（衝撃音）
He went bare-chested without posing!
（大泉）
ポージングなしの おはだけとは…
This is a rare occurrence!
これは貴重なパターンですなぁ
You've got some balls forcing me
to go bare-chested.
（仙左衛門）このわしを
力任せに はだけさすとは―
I'll give you that.
見上げた度胸よ！
（観客）うわああああ！
うえ… これから恵の審査なのに
何か会場の雰囲気が…
MEGUMI
Megumi's about to get her dish evaluated,
but the crowd's just so...
MEGUMI
Kurokiba wasn't just shaking water out of his noodles earlier.
さっきの湯切りで
黒木場が払ったのは湯だけじゃない
The crowd's heightening interest toward Tadokoro-san's dish,
田所さんの料理に傾きかけた会場の
興味 関心 流れ
curiosity,
and the shift in mood...
その全部を断ち切ったんだね
He shook all that off too.
Megumi can't be having an easy time in all this.
これじゃ恵は やりづらいわ
（創真）いや
（涼子）え？
No, not so fast.
Imagine that you're separating the noodles from the strainer, and severing the surface tension.
（恵）
網から麺を離して
表面張力を切るイメージ
MEGUMI
恵！
Megumi!
MEGUMI
この空気にも
押されてないみたいだな
She's not letting herself get
overwhelmed by what's going on.
ええ　集中して
自分の料理とだけ向き合って―
Yes, she's staying focused.
She only sees what she's making.
She reminds me of Yukihira-kun somehow.
何だか 幸平君みたいだわ
Here is my dish.
（恵）私の料理です　どうぞ！
Please have a taste!
Hm, it is an impressive light-broth ramen that is also pleasing to the eye.
（大泉）
うーん　仕上がりも美しい
見事な淡麗スープ
But after having tasted
Kurokiba Ryou's rich seafood ramen,
だが 黒木場リョウの
濃厚魚介ラーメンの後では―
how can hers possibly measure up to its impact?
どうにもインパクトに欠ける
（２人）んんっ！
（観客のどよめき）
So strong.
（審査員Ｂ）強い…
Such powerful umami!
何て強烈な旨味だ！
What?
（観客）ええ？
Isn't it supposed to be a light broth?
（女子生徒Ｂ）
淡麗スープじゃないの？
What is this sweet umami I am
detecting in the clean flavor?
すっきりした味わいの中にある
甘い旨味は？
This combination of ingredients...
（審査員Ｂ）
この具材の組み合わせ―
It's kozuyu!
“こづゆ”か！
Yes!
はい　これは
こづゆを基本に―
This dish used kozuyu as a base.
Finished with the addition of
paitan soup and a soy sauce mix,
白湯スープと
しょうゆダレで仕上げた―
this is my Kozuyu Chicken Soy Sauce Ramen!
こづゆ鶏しょうゆラーメンです
Kozuyu...
こづゆ…
Kozuyu is a traditional regional cuisine of Aizu.
こづゆとは
会津地方に伝わる郷土料理
It's a celebratory dish made from scallop stock.
干し貝柱の だしで作る
祝い事などの席で出される品だ
So you adapted a regional dish into ramen.
With the scallops playing a central role,
郷土料理を
ラーメンにアレンジか
the flavor rests on the solid foundation provided by the paitan soup.
ホタテ貝柱を主役に―
白湯スープが どっしりと
風味の土台を作っている
In addition, the kaeshi employs a mix of light soy sauce
and white soy sauce, which has a pronounced sweetness.
そして かえしは
薄口しょうゆと―
甘みの強い白しょうゆを
合わせたもの
It pairs perfectly with kozuyu,
which is also seasoned with soy sauce!
同じくしょうゆで調味するこづゆと
相性抜群だ！
That still doesn't account for all the umami.
しかし それだけでは
説明できぬ
Where is the rest coming from?
この旨味は一体どこから？
It comes from vegetables.
（恵）え それは野菜から
出たものなんです
Vegetables?
（２人）野菜？
The shiitake mushrooms, burdock root, and green beans you see in the topping
トッピングの しいたけ
ごぼう いんげんなど―
were all dried ingredients that were simmered.
全て干し野菜にして
煮込んだものです
I see!
そうか！　乾燥させることで
旨味が凝縮され―
Drying vegetables concentrates their umami!
Their flavor profiles would change completely from before!
生で使うのとは
全く異なる風味に
All that umami has dissolved into the broth!
そのおいしさが
全て溶け出しているんだ！
I see.
なるほどね　田所お得意の
必殺技ってわけか
It's Tadokoro's specialty!
The delicate sweetness specific to vegetables!
（審査員Ｂ）
野菜特有の繊細な甘み
Who could have foreseen that it could create such a pure yet powerful broth?
それが ここまで清らか
かつ強烈なスープを作り出すとは
I'm so happy that I can't stop smiling!
幸福感で表情筋が戻らぬ
Oh, before you finish the noodles,
あ… 麺を食べ切る前に
その小鉢も試してみてください
please try the paste in the small bowl.
Add as much as you'd like to the broth.
お好みでスープに
加えてみてほしいんです
（２人）ん？
おおおお！
目の覚めるような酸味！
The acidity is eye-opening!
It brings the flavors together even tighter still!
さらに味が
引き締まりおったぁ！
What is this?!
何だね これは？
I combined Aizu chicken meat
会津地鶏の肉に―
with the thinly sliced white part of scallions and pickled plums, along with seasoning.
白髪ねぎと しそと梅干しを合わせ
調味したものです
I thought it'd allow for a fun change of flavor.
味に変化が出て
楽しいかと思ったので
It doesn't just change the flavor!
（大泉）
変化どころではない！
It harmonizes with the kozuyu's delicate flavors
（審査員Ｂ）
こづゆの繊細な風味と
調和しながら―
and heightens the sweetness from the vegetables!
野菜の甘みを
さらに際立たせておる
Hey, that ramen of yours!
（黒木場）おい そのラーメン…
（恵）あ！
俺にも食わせろ！
Let me try it!
O-Okay!
（恵）あ はい～
What a surprise!
（審査員Ｂ）驚きだ
Even though both dishes are seafood ramen,
同じ魚介ラーメンでも―
she was able to create this much umami,
despite taking the dish in a completely different direction!
黒木場リョウのスープ･ド･
ポワソンとは違う方向で―
ここまでの
旨味を出すとは…
I know I can't possibly create a strong flavor like what you might expect
（恵）
濃厚魚介や豚骨みたいな
強い味は―
from rich seafood or pork bone stock.
今の私では とても作れません
It requires great expertise, from preventing fishiness to adjusting the flavors.
臭み取りから 味の調整まで
ものすごい技術が必要ですから
But I thought I could manage to make a "strong" balanced ramen
でも―
こづゆをベースに ホタテと野菜の
旨味を押し出せば―
if I used kozuyu as a base and emphasized the umami of scallops and vegetables!
バランスを崩すことなく―
強いラーメンを作れると
思ったんです！
You knew I'd make a rich type of ramen, and you deliberately chose this dish to compete with mine.
俺が濃厚系ラーメンで来ると
分かってて―
この品を
ぶつけてきやがったのか
This match is getting
interesting, Tadokoro Megumi!
面白(おもしれ)えじゃねえかよ
田所恵ぃ！
Deep within her slight frame
burns a quiet determination.
（大泉）
このきゃしゃな体の その奥には
静かな闘志が燃えていたぁ！
She did not fear her formidable opponent
強敵を恐れずに―
and chose to meet him head-on
in a fierce umami battle!
真っ向から 旨味の
ガチンコ勝負を挑みおったぁ！
（恵）うっ…
Try my ramen too!
味わってみろ
俺のラーメンも！
（恵）ううっ！
What an overpowering fragrance
and umami of the sea!
ものすごい潮の香りと旨味！
I can hardly stay standing!
腰が抜けそう…
How can... How can you make a ramen like this?!
こんな… こんなラーメンが
作れるなんて…
But I don't want to lose!
でも 負けたくない！
What a pitched battle!
（大泉）何という激戦なのだ！
Both of them poured their sheer
willpower into their ramen,
双方がラーメンに込めた精神力が
おいしさとなって具現化するぅ！
and it has manifested itself as flavor!
タコ殴りにしろ！
Beat her dish to a pulp, Soupe de Poisson!
MENACING
スウウウプ･ド･ポワソオオン！
RUMBLE
My Scallops and Pai Tan have
the resolve to defeat any foe,
RUMBLE
私の“ホタテ＆白湯”には―
いかなる強敵にも
立ち向かう覚悟がある！
RUMBLE
no matter how formidable!
（黒木場）エビエビエビエビエビ！
（恵）ホタホタホタ！
Shrimp, shrimp, shrimp!
Scallops, scallops, scallops!
（黒木場）エビエビエビエビエビ！
（恵）ホタホタホタ！
♪～
seki wa kitta nodo kara te ga deru hodo
An intensely burning desire was born
hoshiku nattan da boku ja nai betsu no dareka
But not in me, in someone else
yume to kibou hoka ni nani ga iru to
Where's the me who believed that
omoeta koro no boku wa ima izuko e?
All one needs is to have hopes and dreams
nagai mono ni makarete ushinatta michishirube
Wrapped around something long, my compass was lost
sei to shi no hazama ni wa sunoo duroppu ga sakimidareru
On the border of life and death, snow drops bloom
nanika no machigai de kudakechitte shimatta nara
If by some mistake they get smashed
semete boku no nukegara ni hanataba wo soete
At least put flowers on the empty husk
konna mon ka na konna mon deshou
Is that the way things are? Yes, it is
akirame da to omowaretatte kamawanai kedo
You can call it resignation if you want
boku rashiku nai boku rashiku nai
But that's not me, that's not me
dare ni mo datte tsukureru mon ni kachi wa nai
There's no value in something just anyone could make
～♪
The director's taken up the brush!
総帥(そうすい)が筆を…
Who will be the victor?
勝者は？
Which one will it be?!
どっちなのぉ～
ウッフ
NEXT TIME
THE GENERATION OF PRODIGIES
Next episode: "The Generation of Prodigies."